When people use the word common sense, what they mean is uncommon sense, because the standard
human condition is ignorance and stupidity.
It really is.
The standard human condition is a lot of miscognition.
You can improve your own life by eliminating your miscognitions.
You know the economy sometimes booms and sometimes it doesn't.
And you have to live your life through both episodes.
And our attitude is we just keep swimming and sometimes the tide is with us and
sometimes against.
But we keep swimming either way.
Are you surprised by how long this expansion has lasted?
Of course it's lasted a long time.
But what was really remarkable is we never printed money so much and spent it so fast
and bought back so much debt, public and private.
So this is total terra incognita in economics.
And nobody knew for sure how it was going to work.
Of course it was risky, but it worked.
I don't think they had much else that would work.
They weren't set up to do stimulus.
Too much controversy, democratic inertia, so they had to do something.
And all they had left was just to print money and start buying things.
And that's what they did.
And it turned out to be a very wise response.
And what's even more remarkable is that both Congress and the presidency and
their both parties made the same decision.
They all cooperated.
It was the last time.
Well, it left us licking the Great Recession.
So maybe we ought to try cooperation again since it worked so well once.
If you're a politician in a democracy, of course you want people to print money and
spend it.
And of course it's not a good idea.
The best example, probably in the whole world, is Singapore, which has zero debt.
And never prints money and spends it.
And it's one of the most successful places on earth.
I wish we were like that, but there's only one Singapore.
Will some people now say that federal debt is not a problem at all?
Well, if you believe that, you believe in the tooth fairy.
Because then we don't have to have any more taxes ever.
We'll just print money and live happily ever after.
It obviously won't work.
There comes a point when printing money is counterproductive.
Are we at that point?
Are you concerned?
No, I don't think we are at that point.
But nobody knew where the point was going to come.
And we don't know now.
None of these people who are so pompously sure of things, because we all want
reassurance until they provide it.
Nobody really knows how much of this is too much.
It happened by accident.
We were in desperate trouble.
We were on the eve of a great recession that could have been a great depression,
and then followed by the rise of people like Adolf Hitler and so on and so on.
So we faced a real catastrophe.
The only weapon they had with this huge debt was to print money and spend it.
And they did it.
And they'd draw interest rates down to zero, or real interest rates.
Well, of course, that lifted asset values for the people who were already rich.
Nobody was trying to make the rich richer.
It just was an accidental byproduct of a correct governmental decision made on a bipartisan
basis.
And since it was a weird byproduct that occurred in a weird time, it would go away by itself
and do course.
I can't think of a single example in my whole life where keeping it simple has
worked against us.
We made mistakes, but they weren't because we kept it simple.
We're trying to find intelligent things to do with a torrent of surplus cash.
And we've always had a torrent of surplus cash.
And we're always looking for intelligent things to do with it.
And if we find things that are intelligent to do, we do it.
And if we don't find anything, we let the cash build up.
What the hell is wrong with that?
You know, the game in our kind of life is being able to recognize a good idea
when you rarely get it and rarely is presented to you.
And I think that's something you have to prepare for over a long period.
What is the old saying, that opportunity comes to the prepared mind?
And I don't think you can teach people in two minutes how to have a prepared mind.
But that's the game.
Things we learned 40 years ago, though, will help and recognize the next big idea.
And on opportunity costs, going back to that.
The current freshman economics text, which is sweeping the country,
has right in practically the first page.
And it says, all intelligent people should think primarily in terms of opportunity cost.
And that's obviously correct.
But it's very hard to teach business based on opportunity cost.
It's much easier to teach the capital assets pricing model.
Or you could just punch in numbers and outcome numbers.
And therefore, people teach what is easy to teach instead of what is correct to teach.
It reminds me of Einstein's famous saying.
He says, everything should be made as simple as possible, but no more simple.
Write that down.
Actually, I tend to be a follower of Confucius.
And I think this room is full of Confucian values.
You know, if the first law of Confucianism is filial piety,
particularly toward the elderly males,
you can see why I like that system.
Obviously, considerations of cost are important in business.
And obviously, opportunity costs, which is a doctrine of economics,
really a doctrine of life'smanship, are also very important.
And we've always had that kind of basic thinking.
Of course, capital isn't free.
And of course, you can figure cost of capital when you're borrowing money,
or at least you can figure cost of loans.
But the theorists had to develop some theory for what equity cost.
And there they just went bonkers.
They said, if you earned 100% on capital because you had some marvelous business,
your cost of capital was 100%.
And therefore, you shouldn't look at any opportunity that delivered allows the 80%.
That is the kind of thinking which came out of the capital assets pricing models
and so forth that I've always considered inanity.
What is Berkshire's cost of capital?
We have this damn capital.
It just keeps multiplying and multiplying.
What is its cost?
You have perfectly good old-fashioned doctrines like opportunity cost.
At any given time, when we consider an investment,
we have to compare it to the best alternative investment we have at that time.
We had perfectly good old-fashioned ideas that are very basic to use,
but they weren't good enough for these modern theorists.
So they invented all this ridiculous mathematics,
which concluded that the companies that made the most money had the highest costs of capital.
Well, all I can say is this not for us.
Now, the other half of that question I leave for Mr. Boeber.
What you find, of course, is that the cost of capital is about a quarter percent below
the return promised by any deal that the CEO wants to do.
Very simple.
You know, we have three questions with capital throughout,
leaving aside whether we want to borrow money, which we generally don't want to do.
One is, does it make it more sense to pay it out to the shareholders
than to keep it within the company?
The sub-question on that is if we pay it out,
is it better off to do it by a repurchase or by a dividend?
The test for whether we pay it out in dividends
is can we create more than a dollar of value within the company
with that dollar than paying it out?
And you never know the answer to that,
but so far the answer is judged by results, is yes, we can.
And we think that prospectively we can, but that's a hope on our part,
and it's justified to some extent by past history,
but it's not a certainty.
Once we've crossed that threshold, then do we repurchase stock?
Well, obviously, if you can buy your stock at a significant discount
from conservatively calculated and intrinsic value
and you can buy it in a reasonable quantity, that's a use for capital.
Beyond that, then the question becomes,
if you have the capital and you think you can create more than a dollar,
how do you create the most with the least risk?
And that gets to business risk.
It doesn't get to any calculation of the volatility.
I don't know the risk in seized candy as measured by its stock volatility
because the stock hasn't been outstanding since 1972.
Does that mean I can't determine how risky a business sees this
because we don't have a daily quote on it?
No, I can determine it by looking at the business
and the competitive environment, which it operates and so on.
So once we cross the threshold of deciding
that we can deploy capital so as to create more than a dollar
or a present value for every dollar retained,
then it's just a question of doing the most intelligent thing that you can find.
And that is the cost of every deal we do is measured by the second best deal
that's around or given timing, doing more of some of the things we're already in.
I have listened to cost of capital discussions
at all kinds of corporate board meetings, everything else,
and I've never found anything that made very much sense in it,
except for the fact that it's what they learned in business school
and that's what the consultants talked about.
And most of the board members would nod their head
without knowing what the hell was going on.
And that's been my history with the cost of capital.
Now, moving on to the big ideas,
you know when you've got a big idea and I can't tell you,
you know, exactly what happens within your nervous system
or brain at that time,
but we've had a relatively few big ideas, good ideas over the years.
So I don't know how many you think we've had in aggregate.
I mean, maybe 25 each year.
You took the top 15 out of Berkshire Hathaway.
Most new people wouldn't be here.
So roughly what, every two years?
Yeah, one every year or two.
And sometimes there'll be a bunch of them like in 1973 and four.
But the problem is for us is that big now really means big.
I mean, it has to be billions of dollars
to move the needle very much at Berkshire.
I would say that when I would turn those pages 50 years ago
in the Moody's manuals,
I would know when I had a big idea.
I've got a half a dozen of them
that I keep the Xeroxes from those reports around
from 50 years ago, just because it was so obvious
that they were incredible.
And that happens every now and then.
When I met Rormor Davidson in the January 1951
and he spent four hours or five hours
with me explaining Geico, I knew it was a big idea.
Eight months later, or probably 10 months later,
I wrote an article to the Commercial and Financial
Chronicle on the security I like best.
It was a big idea.
When I found Western Insurance Securities,
I knew it was a big idea.
I couldn't put millions of dollars into it,
but I didn't have millions so it didn't make any difference.
We've seen things subsequently
and we'll see, you know, we have a normal lifespan.
We'll see a few more before we get done.
Actually, I have a real system.
My idea of a truly big idea is one I get
and I call Charlie and he only says no
rather than that's the worst idea I've ever heard of.
If he just says no, it's a hell of an idea.